In this tutorial, we're going to go over
physics problems associated with angular
speed and angular velocity.
So, let's start with this one.
The frequency of a spinning wheel is 30
hertz.
If the diameter of the wheel is 50 cm,
what is the angular speed of the wheel
in radians per second?
So, what equation do we need to
calculate the angular speed?
The angular speed
is represented by this equation, omega.
It's equal to 2 pi f.
You can also use that equation to
calculate the angular velocity.
So, we have the frequency.
The frequency is 30 hertz.
And the frequency represents the number
of cycles that occur per unit time.
So, in this case, the cycles are
rotations or revolutions.
So, if the frequency is 30 hertz, that
means that
the wheel makes 30 revolutions every
second.
Now, when you think of 2 pi, what do you
think of?
One revolution
around a circle
is equal to 360°.
And 360°
is 2 pi radians
because 180 is equal to pi.
So, one revolution around a circle
is 2 pi radians. So, omega
is equal to 2 pi radians per revolution
multiplied by the frequency, which is 30
revolutions per second.
So, notice that the unit revolutions
cancel.
I want to set it up in such a way so you
can see how frequency can give you the
angular speed in radians per second.
So, in this example, it's 2 pi * 30.
So, omega is going to be 60 pi
radians per second.
Now, if you want to get the decimal
value of that,
this is going to be 188.5
rad/s.
So, that's the angular speed in this
problem.
Now, let's move on to part B.
What is the period?
The period is the time
divided by the number of cycles that
occurs.
So, if we have 30 cycles that occur in 1
second,
then the period is 1 second per 30
cycles.
In this case, 30 revolutions.
So, period is simply 1 over F. It's the
reciprocal of the frequency.
So, 1 / 30
is
.033
seconds.
So, what that means is that
the wheel makes one revolution
in .033 seconds.
So, the period tells you the time it
takes to make one revolution or one
complete cycle around the circle.
Whereas the frequency tells you the
number of cycles that can be made in 1
second. So, in 1 second, the wheel is
going to spin 30 times. That's the
frequency.
And the period tells you that
the wheel will spin once every .033
seconds. So, hopefully this clarifies
the definition between period and
frequency. So, frequency tells you how
many cycles will occur in 1 second, and
the period tells you how long it takes
just to make one cycle.
Number two.
What is the linear speed of a wheel that
is rotating at 25 rad/s?
And we're given the radius of the wheel.
It's 30 cm.
So, how can we find the linear speed
of the wheel
given its rotational speed
of 25 rad/s?
So, what should we do?
The equation that we need is this
equation, v is equal to omega times r.
So, all it is is just omega, which is
25, multiplied by the radius of the
wheel, but we need that in meters.
So, to convert 30 cm into meters,
divide it by 100. 30 / 100 is 0.30.
So, 25 * 0.3
is 7.5.
So, the linear speed is 7.5 m/s.
Now, let's make sense of the units.
So, omega
was in radians per second.
And the radius,
I like to think of it as
the length per radian.
So, the radius is 0.3 m, but it's really
0.3 m per radian.
And so, this will give you 7.5 m/s.
Now, for those of you who want to know
why I like to think of the radius as
being the length per radian,
here's why. Let's say
if
we draw an arc.
So, this is going to be s, the arc
length.
And this is the angle theta, and this is
the radius of the circle.
The arc length is equal to the angle in
radians times the radius of the circle.
So, if you solve for R,
the radius is the arc length divided by
the angle.
So, let's say if we have an arc length
of 30 m. And let's say the angle
is
two radians.
So, it's going to be 30 m
per two radians.
So, the radius will be 15 m
per radian.
So, what does this mean?
This is the arc length when the angle is
one radian.
So, when the angle
was two radians,
the arc length
was 30 m.
Now, if you reduce the angle to one
radian,
the arc length will be equal to the
radius, which is 15 m. I wrote minus for
some reason, but
let's uh correct that.
So, that's why I like to think of the
radius as being
the arc length
when the angle is one radian.
So, I think of it as meters per radian.
So, all of this leads me to the
conclusion that
one radian is equal to the length of the
radius.
So, when the angle is one radian,
the arc length of the circle is equal to
the length of the radius of the circle,
which in this example is 15 m.
So, this is useful for conversions.
Let's say if I want to convert linear
speed from radians per second to
rotations per minute or revolutions per
minute.
So, knowing the conversion factor
between radians and meters
is very useful and it's equal to the
radius of the circle.
So, let's say if the radius of the
circle is 8 m,
I can come up with this conversion.
One radian
represents an arc length of 8 m.
If the radius is 8 m, so the radius
would be 8 m per radian.
Let's work on number three.
A disc spins at a rate of 5,000 radians
every 10 minutes.
What is the angular velocity of the disc
in radians per second?
So, to calculate the angular velocity,
we can use this equation.
It's the angular displacement divided by
the change in time.
The angular displacement is
the amount that the disc spins in
radians.
So, it spins a distance of 5,000
And we have the time, which is 10
minutes, but we need that in seconds.
Now, 1 minute is equal to 60 seconds,
which means that 10 minutes is 60 * 10
or 600 seconds.
So, the disc spins 5,000 radians every
600 seconds.
So, therefore,
the angular velocity is 8.33 radians per
second.
So, that's it for part A. Now, let's
move on to part B.
What is the linear velocity of the disc
in meters per second
if the diameter of the disc is 20 cm?
So, we're given the diameter of the disc
is 20 cm.
Now, we need to use that to find the
radius.
The radius of the disc has to be half of
the diameter, so it's 10 cm.
So, we can say the radius
is 10 cm
per radian.
So, that means the length of one radian
or one radian has an arc length of 10
cm.
But we need to convert centimeters into
meters, so we got to divide that by 100.
So, that's 0.1 m per radian.
So, now let's calculate the linear
velocity.
So, V is equal to omega times R.
Omega is 8.33 radians per second.
And the radius is 0.1 m
per radian.
So, the arc length is 0.1 m when the
angle is one radian.
So, these two will cancel.
And then we'll have the units in meters
per second.
So, 8.33 * 0.1
is simply 0.833
m per second.
So, this is the answer to part B.
Now, let's move on to part C.
What is the angular velocity of the
wheel in rotations per minute?
Which is equivalent to revolutions per
minute.
So, how can we find
that answer?
So, all we got to do
is convert the angular velocity from
radians per second
to rotations per minute or simply
revolutions per minute.
So, how can we go about doing that?
Well, let's start with what we have.
8.33
radians per second.
Now, we can convert seconds into
minutes.
60 seconds is equal to 1 minute.
So, the unit seconds cancel.
Next, we can convert radians to
revolutions.
So, it's 2 pi radians per revolution. I
need to put radians on the bottom. So,
one revolution
is equal to 2 pi radians.
And so, now we have the unit revolutions
per minute,
which is basically RPMs.
So, it's 8.33 * 60
divided by
2 pi.
And so, this is going to be 79.
5 rotations per minute.
And that's the answer.
So, here's the last question for this
video.
A wheel with a radius of 1.4 m spins at
an angular speed of 45 rotations per
minute, or revolutions per minute.
What is the linear speed of the wheel in
miles per hour?
Go ahead and try this problem.
So, let's convert it from revolutions
per minute to miles per hour.
So, we have 45
revolutions per minute.
Now, we need to convert minutes to
hours.
60 minutes
is equivalent to 1 hour.
So, that's the first thing we could do.
Now, how do we convert revolutions to
miles?
Well, first, we need to convert
revolutions to radians.
One revolution around a circle
is 2 pi radians.
So, we could cancel the unit
revolutions.
Now, how do we go from radians to
meters?
The radius will help us to do so.
The radius is 1.4 m. So, it's really 1.4
m per radian.
So, what this means is that if we have
an angle of 1 radian, the arc length is
going to be 1.4 m.
So, the radius connects the angle with
the arc length.
So, an angle of 1 radian
equates to an arc length of 1.4 m, so we
can cancel
the unit radians. So, now we have
meters.
Let's convert meters to kilometers.
1,000 m
is equal to 1 km.
And 1 km
is 0.6214
mi.
Now, you can look up these conversions
online.
Or hopefully you know them already.
So, meters cancel.
And also kilometers cancel.
So, what we have left over is miles per
hour.
So, it's 45 * 60
* 2 pi
* 1.4
/ 1,000
* 0.6214.
So,
the wheel is moving at a linear speed of
.76
miles per hour.
So, that's the answer.